富という言葉を聞くと
A discussion of riches
often centers on the danger
まず思い浮かべるのは
of making material wealth
お金や物を重視し過ぎてはいけない
という話かもしれません
the main thing in our life.
今日の聖句にも富が出てきます
Our text today is about riches,
でもこの聖句からは
私たちが持っている物を
but the focus is on how we use
どのように使えばよいかを学べます
the things that we possess.
Let’s go back to our text at Luke 16:9
and read it once again.
もう一度 ルカ 16:9を
読んでみましょう 9節です
It says:
“Also, I say to you:
「また あなたたちに言いますが
“Make friends for yourselves
by means of the unrighteous riches,
この世の富によって友をつくり
そうした物が尽きた時に永遠の住まいに
“so that when such fail,
they may receive you
into the everlasting dwelling places.”
迎え入れてもらえるように
しなさい」とあります
ちょっと難しい聖句かもしれません
There are certain aspects of this text
that some have found difficult to understand.
いろいろな疑問が湧いてきます
For example,
例えば「どうしてクリスチャンが
この世の富を持っていると言えるんだろう
why would a Christian even be in possession
of unrighteous riches?
Who are referred to by the pronoun “they”?
永遠の住まいに迎え入れてくれるのは
いったい誰だろう
Also, what application
is there in this illustration for us?
この例え話から
私たちは何を学べるだろう」
To clarify matters,
it will help us to look at the context.
答えを知るために
聖句の文脈を見てみましょう
Verses 1 through 8
of Luke chapter 16
ルカ 16:1-8で
contain the illustration
of the steward and the unrighteous riches.
イエスは家の管理人についての
例えを話しています
Verses 9 to 13
9節から13節で
provide the application of the illustration.
イエスは例えから学べることを
説明しています
大切な原則が学べます
And that application includes the principles
「ごく小さなことに忠実な人は多くの
ことにも忠実であ［る］」という原則
that ‘the person faithful in least
is faithful in much’
and also that we “cannot slave for God
and for Riches.”
そして「神と富との奴隷に」は
なれないという原則です
To learn how we can benefit
from this teaching of Jesus,
では 次の3つの切り口で
イエスの例え話から
さらに深く学んでみましょう
let’s consider three things.
First of all,
we will examine the illustration.
1つ目に 管理人がしたことを
詳しく見てみます
Second, we will identify the elements.
2つ目に イエスが使った
表現の意味を調べます
And third, we’ll make the application.
3つ目に 私たちにできることを考えます
So first of all,
let’s examine the illustration.
まず1つ目の
管理人がしたことについてです
If we look at Luke 16:1,
it talks about a steward.
16:1に出てくる管理人とは
何をする人でしょうか
If we look at the footnote,
it says this could be a “house manager.”
この聖句の注釈には
「または 『家令』」と書かれています
So it is someone who’s entrusted
with a good deal of responsibility.
管理人には財産の管理など
責任の重い仕事が任されていました
But it says that he is accused
でもこの人は「主人の物を
浪費していると訴えられ」ています
of handling his master’s “goods wastefully.”
Now, the wording of that verse
誰かが悪意を持って
allows for the possibility
that the steward was slandered.
この管理人について事実ではない
訴えをしたのかもしれません
It’s possible the charges were false.
真相は分かりませんが
But Jesus doesn’t focus
on the reason for the steward’s dismissal.
イエスがここで注目してほしかったのは
管理人が解雇された理由ではありません
Rather,
he gives attention
管理人が解雇を告げられた
後にしたことです
to the steward’s reaction.
Verses 2 through 7
2節から7節にはこの管理人が何を考え
何をしたかが書かれています
show us the reasoning of the steward
(knowing that he’s going to be fired).
He says:
‘I’m not strong enough to dig.
管理人はこう考えます 「土堀りも
物乞いもしたくない どうしよう」
‘I’m ashamed to beg.
So how am I going to make a living?’
So he decides to befriend ones
who owe things to his master.
それで 主人に借りがある人の負債を
減らしてあげることにします
One debtor owes 100 measures of olive oil,
ある人には オリーブ油100杯分の
借りがありました
so the steward reduces that debt
to 50 measures.
管理人はそれを50杯分に
減らしてあげます
That’s a reduction
of nearly 300 (1,100 L) gallons of olive oil.
オリーブ油約1100リットル分を
減らしてあげたことになります
別の人には 小麦100袋分の
借りがありました
Another debtor owes his master
100 large measures of wheat.
それを80袋分にしてあげます
He reduces that to 80.
That’s a reduction
of 4,000 (3,700 L) quarts of wheat.
約3000キロ分を
減らしたことになります
That’s a substantial reduction in the debt.
そう考えるとかなりの量だと分かります
Then if we look at verse 8,
16:8を見ると
the master,
on finding out what the steward has done,
主人は管理人のしたことを知って
褒めました なぜでしょうか
calls him “unrighteous,”
管理人は「正しい人とは言えませんが
役立つ知恵を使ったからです」
and yet he commends him
for acting “with practical wisdom.”
So here Jesus is not condoning
イエスは 管理人がしたことを大目に
見るよう言っていたわけではありません
or endorsing the steward’s methods,
nor is he encouraging
crafty business practices.
仕事で不正直なことをしてよいと
言っていたわけでもありません
Jesus simply draws attention
to the need to be farsighted
イエスが教えたかったのは
先のことをよく考えて
and to use practical wisdom.
役立つ知恵を使うことの大切さです
Now let’s identify the elements.
2つ目に イエスが使った表現の
意味について考えてみましょう
We come to our text, verse 9,
where it tells us
9節には「この世の富によって
友をつくり」と書かれています
to ‘use our unrighteous riches
to make friends.’
Jesus doesn’t explain in detail
イエスは「この世の富」という表現を
使っています どういう意味でしょうか
why he refers to the riches as unrighteous.
However, the New International Version {
9節の脚注にあるように
「この世の」という言葉は
when it calls the unrighteous riches
“worldly wealth.”
直訳すると「正しくない」という意味です
In other words,
the unrighteous riches
罪深い人間が所有し使っているので
正しくないと言えます
represent material resources
under the control of sinful humans.
それがこの世の富です
Riches often serve selfish ends,
and they may be gained
多くの人はお金を
自分のために使っています
お金を手に入れるために
汚い手口を使う人や
through crafty or even illegal
business practices.
違法なことをする人もいます
Then Jesus states a reality.
イエスは続けて「そうした物が
尽きた時に」と言いました
He says “when such fail.”
Yes, the value of material wealth is limited,
and it’s temporary.
確かにお金は尽きることがあります
インフレになって
お金の価値が下がることもあります
It can be eaten away by inflation.
Consider the value
例えば 50年前の1アメリカ･ドルの
価値について考えてみましょう
of one U.S. dollar 50 years ago.
If you had 100 dollars (U.S.) in 1969,
1969年に1ドルあれば買えたものは
you would need 692 dollars today
今では約7ドルなければ
買うことができません
to have the same purchasing power.
In 1969,
a gallon (4 L) of gas cost 32 cents.
その頃は1ドルあれば
ガソリンが12リットル
大きなパンが4つ買えました
A loaf of bread cost 23 cents.
お金の価値は不安定です
Yes, riches fail.
And they will definitely fail in the future.
そして将来 必ず尽きることになります
Zephaniah 1:18 says:
ゼパニヤ 1:18にはこうあります
“Neither their silver nor their gold
will be able to save them
「エホバの激怒の日には
銀も金も助けにならない」
in the day of Jehovah’s fury.”
エホバは大患難の時
During the great tribulation,
私たちがどれだけ銀行に預金しているかを
見て裁くわけではありません
we’re not going to be judged
based on the size of our bank account.
Rather, we’re going to be judged
そうではなく 私たちがどれだけ
天に宝を蓄えているかを見て裁くのです
based on our storehouse of spiritual riches
that we have accumulated.
ルカ 16:9に戻りましょう
And that leads to the meaning
of the latter part of verse 9;
節の後半にはこうあります
it says that “they may receive you
「永遠の住まいに
迎え入れてもらえるようにしなさい」
into the everlasting dwelling places.”
What or who
誰が永遠の住まいに
迎え入れてくれるのでしょうか
is referred to by the word “they”?
Is it the riches?
この世の富ですか
そんなはずはありません
Certainly not.
They’re temporary; they’re going to fail.
富はやがて尽きるからです
We have to go back to earlier in the verse
to find the antecedent.
9節の前半にはどう書かれていますか
And it is the word “friends.”
「友をつくり」とあります
So who are these friends?
この友とは誰のことですか
Please open your Bibles to John 3:16.
ヨハネ 3:16を開いて
見てみましょう
There are
only two possibilities of individuals
この聖句を読むと
私たちを永遠の住まいに迎え入れて
くれるのが誰なのかが分かります
who can give us
everlasting dwelling places,
and they’re identified here in this verse.
友はいったい誰でしょうか
John 3:16—it says:
ヨハネ 3:16です
「神は 自分の独り子を与えるほどに
人類を愛したのです
“For God loved the world so much
“that he gave his only-begotten Son,
そのようにして
独り子に信仰を抱く人が皆
“so that everyone exercising faith in him
“might not be destroyed
滅ぼされないで永遠の命を
受けられるようにしました」
but have everlasting life.”
Yes, only God, Jehovah,
神エホバと独り子イエス･キリストだけが
and his Son, Jesus Christ,
私たちを永遠の住まいに
迎え入れることができます
can usher us
into everlasting dwelling places,
天の王国 あるいは地球上のパラダイスの
どちらかに迎え入れてくれます
whether that be the heavenly Kingdom
or the Paradise earth.
3つ目に 私たちに何ができるか
考えてみましょう
Now, let’s make application
of this illustration.
How do we use
the material things of this world
どんなふうにお金や物を使えば
エホバとイエスの友になることが
できるでしょうか
to make friends with Jehovah and Jesus?
Everything we own actually belongs to them.
私たちの持っている物は全部
実際にはお二方の物です
However, each one of us
has a measure of money and material assets
でも私たちはお金や持っている物を
どんなふうに使うか
that we are free to use as we please.
自分で自由に決めることができます
So to make friends with Jehovah and Jesus,
エホバとイエスに喜んでもらえるような
使い方をすれば
we have to use those things in a way
お二方の友になることができます
that brings their approval.
Our contributions
don’t have to be in the form of cash.
エホバに寄付できるのは
お金だけではありません
In Jesus’ illustration,
the debt was olive oil and wheat.
イエスの例え話には
オリーブ油や小麦が出てきました
The unrighteous riches
might even be coconuts.
そうした物もこの世の富に含まれます
A brother in southern India
owns a coconut farm.
インドのある兄弟は
ココナツ農園を持っていました
He contributed a large number of coconuts
兄弟は遠隔翻訳事務所の兄弟たちが
to the local remote translation office.
ココナツを買っていることを
知っていました
He reasoned, “The office is going
to have to spend money and buy coconuts.”
それで自分の農園でできたココナツを
寄付することにしました
So his supplying the coconuts directly
たくさんのココナツです
would help his contribution go further
それを売って手に入れたお金を
寄付するよりも
than it would if he sold the coconuts
and gave the office the cash.
現物を寄付する方がよいと思ったのです
That is practical wisdom.
まさに役立つ知恵です
Now, if we go back to Luke chapter 16,
では ルカ 16章に戻って
let’s look at verse 10.
10節を見てみましょう
Here it’s interesting that the principle
ここには「ごく小さなことに忠実な人は
‘the person faithful in what is least
will be faithful in much’
多くのことにも忠実であ［る］」と
書かれています
この世の富についての話の中で
この原則が出てくるのは面白いですね
was given in the context
of our use of material riches.
So we cannot take
this responsibility lightly.
この世の富をどう使うかは重要です
Notice what it says in verse 11.
11節にもこうあります
It says: “Therefore,
if you have not proved yourselves faithful
「それで あなたたちが
この世の富に関して
忠実であることを示していないなら
“in connection with the unrighteous riches,
誰があなたたちに
本当に価値あるものを託すでしょうか」
who will entrust you with what is true?”
Yes, the way we use
our monetary riches or goods
この世の富
つまりお金や物をどう使うかで
大切なものを託してもらえるか
どうかが決まります
will affect the extent
to which the things that are true,
エホバへの奉仕という本当に価値ある
ものを託してもらえるかどうかです
such as Kingdom interests,
are entrusted to us.
Therefore,
let’s remember the key point
イエスが話した管理人の例え話の
大切なポイントを覚えておきましょう
of Jesus’ illustration
of the unrighteous steward.
No matter how much or how little
of this world’s goods
お金や物をたくさん持っているとしても
あるいはわずかしか持っていないとしても
we have under our control,
we want to use them
to strengthen our relationship
最高の友 エホバとイエスとの
友情を強めるために
with our best Friends,
Jehovah and Jesus.
この世の富を使っていきましょう